Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Congress of Industrial Organizations PE.005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Congress of Industrial Organizations
1936-1987
1936-1959
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.005
5.5 Linear Feet in 5 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) (1936-1987, bulk 1936-1959) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The CIO was founded in 1935 as part of the American Federation of Labor (AFL) and known as the Committee for Industrial Organization. Formalizing a break with the AFL over disputes in how to organize industrial workers, the CIO held its first convention in 1938, and it was there that it changed its name to the Congress of Industrial Organizations. The collection consists of contracts, agreements, and constitutions, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. Material comes from the international and national body of the CIO but also its regional, state, and city councils, most notably, the Greater New York CIO Council and the New York State Industrial Union Council.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) (1936-1987, bulk 1936-1959) consists of agreements, contracts, constitutions, by-laws, and reports, as well as printed ephemera such as clippings, flyers, broadsides, leaflets, programs, and pamphlets produced by the CIO nationally as well as by its city, state and regional industrial councils.
Series I: National Council Files, 1936-1987, consists of material from various committees and departments of the CIO, including the Committee on Civil Rights, the Department of Education and Research, the Political Action Committee, as well as the early formation of the CIO, known as the Committee for Industrial Organization formed in 1935 as part of the American Federation of Labor (AFL).
Series II: City, State and Regional Industrial Councils, 1938-1959, consists of printed material from the CIO's city, state and regional industrial councils. Notably, this series contains files from the Greater New York CIO Council and the New York State Industrial Council.
Historical Note
The Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) was originally conceived in 1935 within the American Federation of Labor (AFL) as the Committee for Industrial Organization. After formalizing a break with the AFL, stemming from disagreements in how to organize industrial workers, the CIO established itself an independent federation in 1938. John L. Lewis was an influential force and served as president until 1940, when Philip Murray of the United Steelworkers of America succeeded him. The first unions chartered by the CIO were the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America, the United Mine Workers of America, and the United Steelworkers of America. In 1955, the AFL, under the leadership of George Meany, merged with the CIO, led by Walter Reuther. As of 2009, the AFL-CIO represented over 11 million members.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: National Council Files, 1936-1987
Series II: City, State and Regional Industrial Councils, 1938-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. There is no accession record associated with this collection.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Labor unions; Labor unions -- Organizing -- United States.; Labor movement.; Brochures.; Circular letters.; Labor unions -- Organizing -- New York (N.Y.); Articles.; Fliers (printed matter); Pamphlets.; Constitutions.; Printed ephemera.; Publications (documents); Press releases.; Rosters.; Reports.; Speeches.; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.). Political Action Committee; Greater New York Industrial Union Council; New York City CIO Council; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); American Federation of Labor. Congress for Industrial Organization
- Series I: National Council Files, 1936-1987; 1936-1959; 3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
  - Berman, John S.: Fueling the Fire: The Role of the Media in the Purge of the CIO: 1946-50 (Unpublished Manuscript), undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical and Historical Material, 1952, undated (Box 1)
  - CIO News, 1943-1945, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1938-1939 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1940 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1942-1948 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1951-1955 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Circular Letters, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Conferences: Reports and Speeches, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Fliers, 1936-1937, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Legal Department, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Pamphlets and Publications, 1936-1938 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Press Releases, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Committee for Industrial Organization: Rosters, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Civil Rights, 1953, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee on Economic Policy, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee on Fair Labor Standards, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Latin American Affairs, 1948, 1952, undated (Box 1)
  - Committee to Abolish Racial Discrimination, 1943 (Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 3)
  - Community Relations Department, 1953, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Conventions: Fliers, Press Releases, Programs, Resolutions, 1939-1951 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Conventions: Fliers, Press Releases, Programs, Resolutions, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1938-1955 (Box 1)
  - Cost of Living Committee, 1944 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research, 1944-1955, undated (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Circular Letters, 1946-1955 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Pamphlets and Publications, circa 1940-1945 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Pamphlets and Publications, circa 1946-1949 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Pamphlets and Publications, circa 1950-1955 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Steward's Guides and Manuals, 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Department of Education and Research: Steward's Guides and Manuals, 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Department of International Affairs, 1944-1945, undated (Box 1)
  - Directories and Rosters, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Economic Division, 1941 (Box 1)
  - European Office, undated (Box 1)
  - Fair Labor Standards Committee, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Film Division, 1949, 1955, undated (Box 1)
  - Fliers, undated (Box 1)
  - Handbook and Rules, 1941, 1947, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Housing Committee, 1938, 1940 (Box 2)
  - International Committee, 1951-1953, 1955, undated (Box 2)
  - Legal Department, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Legal Department, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Legislative Committee, 1938, 1940, undated (Box 2)
  - Legislative Department, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Maritime Committee, 1944, 1955, undated (Box 2)
  - National CIO Committee to Abolish Discrimination, 1943-1948, undated (Box 2)
  - National CIO Community Services Committee, 1948-1949, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - National CIO Community Services Committee: Pamphlets and Publications, 1943, 1953, undated (Box 2)
  - National CIO War Relief Committee, 1943-1944, undated (Box 2)
  - National War Labor Board, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1941, 1946, 1949, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications (General CIO), 1942-1953 (Box 2)
  - Pension Plan, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Brochures, circa 1940s, undated (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Conferences: Proceedings, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Elections: Memoranda and Reports, 1951-1955 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Fliers, undated (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Pamphlets and Publications, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Pamphlets and Publications, 1945-1948 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Pamphlets and Publications, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Pamphlets and Publications: "Facts" Series, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Posters, 1944-1946, undated (Box 2)
  - Political Action Committee: Press Releases, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Political Action Committee: Publications Relating to, 1946-1949, undated (Box 3)
  - Political Action Committee: Speeches and Statements, 1944-1948 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases, 1936-1945 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases, 1951-1955 (Box 3)
  - Publicity and Publications Departments: Pamphlets and Publications, 1939, undated (Box 3)
  - Publicity and Publications Departments: Pamphlets and Publications, 1940-1945 (Box 3)
  - Publicity and Publications Departments: Pamphlets and Publications, 1946-1955 (Box 3)
  - Publications Relating to, 1941-1953, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Radio Programs, 1945, 1947, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Reports, 1936, 1941, 1945-1947 (Box 3)
  - Social Security Committee, 1939-1940 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and Statements, 1940-1945, 1949, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Union Label Committee, undated (Box 3)
  - Veterans Committee, undated (Box 3)
  - Wage Research Committee, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Wage Research Committee, 1945-1947 (Box 3)
  - Wage Stabilization, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
  - Women's Auxiliary, undated (Box 3)
- Series II: City, State and Regional Industrial Councils, 1938-1959; 3.5 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 1 shared manuscript box
  - Birmingham Industrial Union Council, undated (Box 3)
  - British Columbia Industrial Union Council, 1940 (Box 3)
  - California Industrial Union Council/ California State CIO Council, 1948, 1950, 1954 (Box 3)
  - California Industrial Union Council/ California State CIO Council: Conventions, 1941-1942, 1950, 1958 (Box 3)
  - California Industrial Union Council/ California State CIO Council: Pamphlets and Publications, 1945-1948, undated (Box 3)
  - California Industrial Union Council/ California State CIO Council: Research Department (I), 1946 (Box 3)
  - California Industrial Union Council/ California State CIO Council: Research Department (II), 1946 (Box 3)
  - Cleveland Industrial Union Council, 1946 (Box 3)
  - Cook County Industrial Union Council, 1953 (Box 3)
  - Genesee County CIO Political Research Committee (Michigan), undated (Box 3)
  - Greater Los Angeles Industrial Union Council, 1948-1952, undated (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Circular Letters, 1940-1944, undated (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Circular Letters, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Circular Letters, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Circular Letters, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Conferences, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Constitutions, 1940-1944, undated (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: "Council Digest" Meeting Minutes, 1942-1946 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Directory and Manual, 1943, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Fliers, undated (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Pamphlets and Publications, 1941-1945, undated (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Political Action Committee, 1944-1946, undated (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Press Releases, 1940, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Relief Fund, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - Greater New York CIO Council: Reports, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - Illinois State Industrial Union Council, 1942, 1948, 1956 (Box 4)
  - Indiana State Industrial Union Council, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Kentucky State Industrial Union Council, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Lehigh County Industrial Union Council, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Lycoming County Industrial Union Council, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Maryland and District of Columbia Industrial Union Council, 1938 (Box 4)
  - Maryland Industrial Union Council, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Massachusetts State CIO Industrial Union Council, 1949-1953 (Box 4)
  - Michigan CIO Council, 1942-1958, undated (Box 4)
  - New Jersey State Industrial Union Council/ New Jersey State CIO Council, 1950-1957, undated (Box 4)
  - New Jersey State Industrial Union Council/ New Jersey State CIO Council: Conventions, 1946-1955 (Box 4)
  - New Jersey State Industrial Union Council/ New Jersey State CIO Council: Executive Board Minutes, 1957-1959 (Box 4)
  - New Jersey State Industrial Union Council/ New Jersey State CIO Council: Political Action Committee, 1950, 1954, undated (Box 4)
  - New York City CIO Council, 1949-1953, undated (Box 5)
  - New York City CIO Council, 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: CIO Reporter, 1944-1945 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Constitutions, 1940-1950, 1954 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1938 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1944 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1945 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1949 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1953 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1956 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1957 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Conventions, 1958 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Fliers, undated (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Legislative Program and Reports, 1942-1945 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Pamphlets and Publications, 1951, 1957, undated (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Political Action Committee, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Resolutions, 1944-1947, undated (Box 5)
  - New York State Industrial Union Council/ New York State CIO Council: Speeches, 1944, undated (Box 5)
  - Ohio CIO Council, 1938-1947, 1951, undated (Box 5)
  - Ohio CIO Council: Constitutions, 1940-1944, 1953 (Box 5)
  - Ohio CIO Council: Political Action Committee, 1944-1950, undated (Box 5)
  - Ohio CIO Council: Workers' Education Conference, 1940 (Box 5)
  - Oregon State Industrial Union Council, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Pennsylvania Industrial Union Council, 1940, 1945-1955 (Box 5)
  - Pontiac Industrial Union Council, undated (Box 5)
  - San Francisco CIO Council, 1941, 1946, 1951 (Box 5)
  - Texas State Industrial Union Council/ Texas State CIO Council, 1951-1954 (Box 5)
  - Washington State Industrial Union Council, 1940, 1945 (Box 5)